<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on </title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Darren L Dahly - All rights reserved</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Should we really censure people for ad hominem attacks in scientific discourse </title>
      <link>/post/2018-05-12-pnas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-05-12-pnas/</guid>
      <description>“Individuals engaging in ad hominem attacks in scientific discourse should be subject to censure.”
That quote is taken from an editorial about errors in science that recently appeared in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences (Issues with data and analyses: Errors, underlying themes, and potential solutions. Andrew W. Brown, Kathryn A. Kaiser, and David B. Allison. PNAS March 13, 2018. 115 (11) 2563-2570; published ahead of print March 12, 2018).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Magical clusters</title>
      <link>/post/cluster/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/cluster/</guid>
      <description>I was greeted today with the news that there are 5, not 2, types of diabetes. This is earth-shattering if you are a diabetologist or diabetes researcher. However, I soon as I saw the term “data-driven clustering” I knew I could probably relax.
For the uninitiated, data-driven clustering techniques can seem magical. The basic premise is that you take a sample, measure lots of things about them, and then feed all those data into an algorithm that will divide your sample into mutually exclusive groups.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can social media be useful for scientists?</title>
      <link>/post/2018-02-28-socialmedia/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-02-28-socialmedia/</guid>
      <description>I have been blogging and using Twitter as a scientist since 2010. By that point it was pretty obvious that the internet was radically changing how scientists could engage with the public and each other, and thus science blogging had become quite popular. Like a lot of people, I wanted to write about how studies from my areas of expertise were reported in the media, and my first substantial blog post was about a large epidemiological study of homebirths in the UK.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New workshop for citizen scientists</title>
      <link>/post/2017-10-04-citizen-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-10-04-citizen-science/</guid>
      <description>I am happy to announce that in the new year we will be running a series of workshops for Cork&amp;rsquo;s Citizen Scientists. In contrast to the small series of lectures we ran this year, the new workshops will be completely focused on supporting local citizen scientists in their efforts to answer real questions with real data.
The 2-hour workshops will take place every 2 weeks (on Saturday evenings), for approximately 6 months.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sex differences</title>
      <link>/post/2017-09-12-sex-differences/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-09-12-sex-differences/</guid>
      <description>The Introduction Remember the whole Google Memo thing that happened a hundred years ago? Its central argument (as far as I could tell) was that the large male to female sex ratios we observe in Tech can be reasonably explained by small differences in the sex-specific probability distributions of innate characteristics. Thus Google’s attempts to increase diversity were silly at best, perhaps harmful or unjust, and largely due to a culture of political correctness that was oppressive to “conservative viewpoints”.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Response Heterogeneity</title>
      <link>/post/2017-08-11-response-heterogeneity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-08-11-response-heterogeneity/</guid>
      <description>A colleague in food science recently sent me a narrative review outlining some of the challenges in their field (Cassidy and Minihane, 2017, Am J Clin Nutr). One of these was “extensive heterogeneity in the response to increased intake [of flavonoids]”.
Response heterogeneity is often highlighted to justify the need for precision medicine. The argument is that we need precision medicine to identify and treat the people that we know will respond well to a particular treatment, and not bother treating those who won&amp;rsquo;t respond.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rater effects</title>
      <link>/post/rater_effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/rater_effects/</guid>
      <description>I was recently asked to help analyze some assessment data. There were 50 people applying for seven positions. Each person’s application materials were scored by three people, randomly chosen from a larger group of raters. I was asked to help account for the fact that some raters might have a tendency to give higher or lower than average scores.
If you want to play along, you can download the data here:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Log Log Regression</title>
      <link>/post/loglog/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/loglog/</guid>
      <description>When using linear regression, when should you log-transform your data?
Many people seem to think that any non-Gaussian, continuous variables should be transformed so that the data “look more normal.” Linear regression does in fact assume the errors are normally distributed, but it is fairly robust to violations of this assumption, and there are no such assumptions regarding the predictor variables. What is often ignored or misunderstood is the impact that variable transformations have on the linearity assumption of regression models, and on coefficient interpretation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting an interview</title>
      <link>/post/2017-05-09-interviews/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-05-09-interviews/</guid>
      <description>To get a job, you have to get an interview. Who knows what will happen at that point, but securing an interview is at least partly in your own hands. Having just finished shortlisting the applicants to a postdoctoral research post I recently advertised, here are my thoughts on how to get your foot further in the door. None of this is original. It’s just fresh on my mind.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In Defense of DAGs</title>
      <link>/post/2017-03-30-dags/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-03-30-dags/</guid>
      <description>Professors Nancy Krieger (NK) and George Davey Smith (GDS) recently published an editorial in the IJE titled The tale wagged by the DAG: broadening the scope of causal inference and explanation for epidemiology. In it, they argue that causal inference in epidemiology is dominated by an approach characterised by counterfactuals (or potential outcomes) and directed acyclic graphs (DAGs); and that this hegemony is limiting the scope of our field, and preventing us from adopting a more useful, pluralistic view of causality.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Your science is justified by the question, not the answer</title>
      <link>/post/2017-03-21-prereg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-03-21-prereg/</guid>
      <description>Registration of clinical trials, prior to any patient recruitment, is now common. Though trial registrations often omit the important details regarding their proposed analyses (despite advice to the contrary), most trialists seem to agree, at least in principle, that you should transparently describe your plans for clinical trial data before they are collected. Unfortunately, this remains a foreign concept in other areas of clinical and public health research.
Before I started working as a biostatistician involved in clinical trials, I worked with birth cohort studies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upcoming R workshop</title>
      <link>/post/2017-03-13-r_courses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-03-13-r_courses/</guid>
      <description>The Clinical Research Facility Cork is sponsoring a free, two-day introduction to data analysis using the R statistical programming language on March 30th and 31st (Th, F), from 09:30 to 16:30 in the Western Gateway Building 3.71. Places are available on a first-come, first-serve basis, and there is space for 10 participants. Please email me at ddahly@ucc.ie to reserve a place.
The course is intended for people who are new to R, but at least somewhat familiar with other statistical software such as Stata or SPSS.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cause vs. Consequence</title>
      <link>/post/2017-02-04-consequentialism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-02-04-consequentialism/</guid>
      <description>I have, for some time, wanted to respond to Sandro Galea&amp;rsquo;s essay on a Consequentialist Epidemiology, published in 2013 (!) in the American Journal of Epidemiology. It is hard to argue against the importance of consequentialism for academic epidemiology. It is equally hard to dismiss Galea&amp;rsquo;s concerns about our lack of influence with funders and policy makers. However, my views beyond this diverge from Professor Galea&amp;rsquo;s, and in the spirit of his &amp;ldquo;provocation,&amp;rdquo; I would like to respectfully offer an alternate perspective.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stata Workshop (2016)</title>
      <link>/post/2017-04-13-stata_workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-04-13-stata_workshop/</guid>
      <description>Introduction to data analysis with Stata On May 24, 2017, the Clinical Research Facility Cork will host a one-day workshop featuring Stata data analysis and statistical software. It will take place in the Brookfield Health Sciences Building (G07) at University College Cork. The workshop will be led by Dr Darren Dahly, the Principal Statistician at the CRF-C.
The workshop is free for registered PhD students. Otherwise, the cost is 75 EUR and can be paid by credit card or purchase order (for UCC based attendees).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The perils of exploratory data analysis</title>
      <link>/post/2017-02-03-exploratory/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-02-03-exploratory/</guid>
      <description>Is it ever ok to conduct an exploratory data analysis, for the purpose of &amp;ldquo;generating hypotheses&amp;rdquo;?
This question was motivated by a new Retraction Watch piece, Backlash prompts prominent nutrition researcher to reanalyze multiple papers. It covers the backlash to an earlier blog post by Brian Wansink, who wrote about two early career researchers, one of whom took on several &amp;ldquo;extra&amp;rdquo; projects, vs. another who refused (The Grad student who never said no).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An academic career path</title>
      <link>/post/2015-08-13-career-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-08-13-career-talk/</guid>
      <description>As of today I am a Senior Lecturer at the Clinical Research Facility Cork. I am feeling reflective. In the 5 short years following my PhD, I went from the USA, to England, to Brazil, to Ireland. I have gone from Lecturer, to Post-Doc, to Senior Lecturer, in that order. I started in pursuit of a career in public health nutrition, but now work primarily as a biostatistician conducting clinical research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cork R-Users Group - First Meet-Up</title>
      <link>/post/2015-08-10-first-r-users/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-08-10-first-r-users/</guid>
      <description>Thanks to all of you for joining the Cork R-Users group, especially the thirteen real-life human R-Users who met for the first time last week at our inaugural meet-up.
I was happy to see a diverse group. I thought we were well balanced between academia and industry, and between statistics and data science. There were software engineers, biostatisticians, ecologists, data scientists, PhD students, and systems administrators. We had people with 10 plus years of experience with R, and people who had never used it but wanted to see what the fuss was about.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why share the data?</title>
      <link>/post/2015-06-15-sharing-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-06-15-sharing-data/</guid>
      <description>Research data should be shared. This view is widespread in academia and common among research funders. Regardless, most research datasets remain locked away. Sometimes data are held back for less than admirable reasons, but they can also be held back with good intent. For example, access to data is sometimes restricted in order to maximize opportunities for early career researchers to publish papers using the data. I believe this is instead counter-productive for ECRs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is overweight, really?</title>
      <link>/post/2015-01-05-who-obesity-infographic/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jan 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2015-01-05-who-obesity-infographic/</guid>
      <description>The image below is from the WHO, and I don&amp;rsquo;t like it.
The top figure represents both overweight and obese people. According to the WHO, a person with a body mass index (BMI) of 25 or greater is overweight, while a person with a BMI of 30 or more is obese. The WHO arrived at these numbers partly due to research comparing health outcomes across people with different BMIs. These studies produce graphs like this one, which looks at mortality rate as a function of BMI.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What do we know about body composition in healthy infants?</title>
      <link>/post/2014-12-17-infant-body-composition/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2014 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-12-17-infant-body-composition/</guid>
      <description>Click to download the PDF.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>River Plots</title>
      <link>/post/2014-11-25-river-plots/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-11-25-river-plots/</guid>
      <description>There are many ways to look at the relationship between two categorical variables.
A simple contingency table will often do the job.
library(gmodels) macroTable &amp;lt;- (data$macro, data$macroCust, dnn = c(&amp;quot;Birth Weight&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Customised Centile&amp;quot;) CrossTable(macroTable, digits = 2, prop.t = F, prop.chisq = F)  Mosaic plots are pretty cool.
library(vcd) mosaic(macroTable, labeling = labeling_list(sep = &amp;quot;, &amp;quot;, cols = 1), margins = c(bottom = 7), legend = T, shade = T)  However, something I&amp;rsquo;ve really come to appreciate is the river plot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prediction vs Risk Factors</title>
      <link>/post/2014-11-11-prediction-vs-risk-factors/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2014 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2014-11-11-prediction-vs-risk-factors/</guid>
      <description>Seán Millar and I were recently asked to review a paper. In his review, he pointed out the difference in predicting an outcome vs. identifying risk factors for an outcome. It is an important point I have clumsily tried to convey in other reviews, but he put it so nicely I asked if I could quote him here (I&amp;rsquo;ve made a few small editorial changes, mainly intended to generalize what he wrote).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where “Hunter-Gatherer Energetics and Human Obesity” gets it wrong</title>
      <link>/post/2012-08-31-hunter-gatherer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Aug 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2012-08-31-hunter-gatherer/</guid>
      <description>There is a recent PLoS ONE article on obesity getting quite a bit of attention. The article, Hunter-Gatherer Energetics and Human Obesity, reports research looking at total energy expenditure in a sample of adults from a Tanzanian hunter-gatherer tribe, the Hadza. Given their “traditional physically active lifestyle” the authors expected that Hadza to have lower body fat and to expend more energy than modern, Western populations, and the aim the research was to see if this was in fact true.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Helpful resources for peer-review of statistical methods</title>
      <link>/post/2012-07-06-statistical-rigor/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jul 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2012-07-06-statistical-rigor/</guid>
      <description>Have you been asked to peer-review the statistical aspects of a research paper? Here are some helpful resources.
Statistical reviewing for medical journals
Use of check lists in assessing the statistical content of medical studies
Guidelines for Reporting of Statistics in European Urology
Quality and value: Statistics in peer-review
Statistical errors in medical research – a review of common pitfalls
Statistical reviewing policies of medical journals
Methods and Biostatistics: a concise guide for peer reviewers</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to lose weight</title>
      <link>/post/2012-08-09-lose_weight/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jul 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2012-08-09-lose_weight/</guid>
      <description>People who know me know that I hate being asked how to lose weight. Yes, I study nutrition for a living. Yes, I teach a class called Obesity and Public Health. This doesn’t mean I have a satisfying answer to the question of how to lose weight. Instead, I have a very unsatisfying answer.
The Three Key Messages There are no quick fixes Your body regulates energy intake and expenditure in a manner that allows your weight to fluctuate within a small range.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The catch-up dilemma</title>
      <link>/post/2012-06-08-catchup/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2012-06-08-catchup/</guid>
      <description>I eventually had to stop telling people that I studied obesity. Backyard barbeques, grocery stores, a friend’s house, it didn’t matter. It was always the same question. “How do I lose weight?” Again, and again, and again.
It’s not the question I find depressing; it’s the answer. If you want to lose weight, and keep it off, you have to radically change how you live your life. Nobody wants to hear that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epidemiological Flaws In The Case Against Co-Sleeping</title>
      <link>/post/2012-04-30-cosleeping/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2012-04-30-cosleeping/</guid>
      <description>I recently read a paper (via @yusunbin) in the American Journal of Public Health concluding (among other things) that “infants sharing a sleep surface” was a contributor to Sudden Unexpected Infant Deaths (SUIDs; a classification that includes deaths due to SIDS, suffocation, or undetermined causes).
I was initially interested in the paper because, as a new parent, I know that the benefits and dangers of co-sleeping are hotly debated. On the one hand, there are well-meaning people that promote safe co-sleeping because it encourages breastfeeding (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tips for getting a fellowship as an early career statistician</title>
      <link>/post/2012-04-04-fellowship-tips/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Apr 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2012-04-04-fellowship-tips/</guid>
      <description>The Young Statisticians Section of the Royal Statistical Society recently hosted a Funding Day for Career Young Medical/Bio-Statisticians (flyer here). The aim was to help early career statisticians identify and successfully apply for MRC and NIHR fellowships.
Prof. Deborah Ashby (Chair in Medical Statistics and Clinical Trials at Imperial College) started the day with an excellent talk about the opportunities a fellowship provides for early career statisticians. She was followed by Peter Thompson (Programme Manager – NIHR) and Mark Pitman (Programme Manager – MRC) who outlined their respective organizations’ strategies, and described the fellowships that were availible for statisticians.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How can we fix scientific publishing?</title>
      <link>/post/2012-02-12-broken-publishing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2012-02-12-broken-publishing/</guid>
      <description>People often question the equity and efficiency of how research is published. One problem is the cost to access scientific research. Publishers sell a product that is initially provided to them for free. While the publisher pays to administrate peer-review of the paper, the real value-added contribution is provided free of charge by editors and reviewers. The publisher incurs costs for dissemination, but these have certainly come down over time. However, the journal prices do not seem to reflect these savings, a clear indicator of monopolistic behaviour that has led to massive profits for some publishers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining Obesity For Public Health Research Purposes</title>
      <link>/post/2012-02-06-defining-obesity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2012-02-06-defining-obesity/</guid>
      <description>Obesity can be defined as an accumulation of adipose tissue that deleteriously impacts health and well-being. How do we then measure obesity, as it’s defined here, for epidemiological studies aimed at identifying causes of obesity that may eventually form the basis for later public health intervention?
To do this, we need 2 things: a measure of adipose tissue; and a cut-point that indicates a level of adipose tissue that we think leads to “poor health and well-being.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are homebirths really risky?</title>
      <link>/post/2011-12-04-home-birth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2011 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2011-12-04-home-birth/</guid>
      <description>Mums thinking about homebirth were greeted this week with a host of conflicting headlines regarding its safety in the UK.
Some were alarming.
Home birth ‘carries higher risk’ for first-time mothers – The BBC
Home birth risks up for new mums – The Sun
First time mothers warned over home birth risks – The Telegraph
First-time mothers who opt for home birth face triple the risk of death or brain damage in child – The Daily Mail</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>